<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC5280 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6487 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6487.xml">
]>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-huston-sidr-validity-01.txt"
     updates="6487"
     ipr="trust200902" >
  <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
  <?rfc toc="yes" ?>
  <?rfc compact="yes" ?>
  <?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
  <?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
  <?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
  <?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>

  <front>
    <title abbrev="RPKI Validation">Update to RPKI Validation</title>

    <author fullname="Geoff Huston" initials="G." surname="Huston">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cordelia St</street>
          <city>South Brisbane</city> <region>QLD</region> <code>4101</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+61 7 3858 3100</phone>
        <email>gih@apnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="George Michaelson" initials="G." surname="Michaelson">
      <organization abbrev="APNIC">Asia Pacific Network Information Centre</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6 Cordelia St</street>
          <city>South Brisbane</city> <region>QLD</region> <code>4101</code>
          <country>Australia</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+61 7 3858 3100</phone>
        <email>ggm@apnic.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2015"/>
    <abstract>
    
      <t>This document updates the RPKI certificate validation procedure
      as specified in Section 7.2 of RFC6487.</t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>This document updates the RPKI certificate validation
      procedure as specified in Section 7.2 of <xref
      target="RFC6487"></xref>, by replacing the section 7.2 of <xref
      target="RFC6487"></xref> with the specification contained
      here.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="The RPKI Certification Path Validation">

      <t>Validation of signed resource data using a target resource
      certificate, and a specific set of number resources, consists of
      verifying that the digital signature of the signed resource data
      is valid, using the public key of the target resource
      certificate, and also validating the resource certificate in the
      context of the RPKI, using the path validation process.  This
      path validation process verifies, among other things, that a
      prospective certification path (a sequence of n certificates)
      satisfies the following conditions:
      <list> <t><list style="numbers">

        <t>for all 'x' in {1, ..., n-1}, the Subject of certificate
        'x' is the Issuer of certificate ('x' + 1); <vspace
        blankLines="1"/></t>

        <t>certificate '1' is issued by a trust anchor; <vspace
        blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>certificate 'n' is the certificate to be validated; and
        <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>for all 'x' in {1, ..., n}, certificate 'x' is valid for
        the specific set of resources.</t>

        </list></t></list></t>

      <t>RPKI validation for a specific set of resources entails
      verifying that all of the following conditions hold, in addition
      to the Certification Path Validation criteria specified in
      Section 6 of <xref target="RFC5280"></xref>: <vspace
      blankLines="1" /> <list><t><list style="numbers">

        <t>The certificate can be verified using the Issuer's public
        key and the signature algorithm <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>The current time lies within the certificate's Validity
        From and To values. <vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>The certificate contains all fields that MUST be present,
        as specified by <xref target="RFC6487" />, and contains values
        for selected fields that are defined as allowable values by
        this specification.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>No field, or field value, that the <xref target="RFC6487"
        /> specification defines as MUST NOT be present is used in the
        certificate.<vspace blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>The Issuer has not revoked the certificate. A revoked
        certificate is identified by the certificate's serial number
        being listed on the Issuer's current CRL, as identified by the
        CRLDP of the certificate, the CRL is itself valid, and the
        public key used to verify the signature on the CRL is the same
        public key used to verify the certificate itself.<vspace
        blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>The resource extension data contained in this certificate
        "encompasses" the entirety of the resources in the specific
        resource set ("encompass" in this context is defined in
        Section 7.1 of <xref target="RFC6487" />).<vspace
        blankLines="1" /></t>

        <t>The Certification Path originates with a certificate issued
        by a trust anchor, and there exists a signing chain across the
        Certification Path where the Subject of Certificate 'x' in the
        Certification Path matches the Issuer in Certificate 'x + 1'
        in the Certification Path, and the public key in Certificate
        'x' can verify the signature value in Certificate 'x+1'.</t>
        </list></t> </list></t>

        <t>A certificate validation algorithm MAY perform these tests
        in any chosen order.</t>

        <t>There exists the possibility of encountering certificate
        paths that are arbitrarily long, or attempting to generate
        paths with loops as means of creating a potential
        denial-of-service (DOS) attack on an Relying Party (RP).  An
        RP executing this procedure MAY apply further heuristics to
        guide the certification path validation process to a halt in
        order to avoid some of the issues associated with attempts to
        validate such malformed certification path structures.
        Implementations of resource certificate validation MAY halt
        with a validation failure if the certification path length
        exceeds a locally defined configuration parameter.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="Security Considerations">
    
      <t>This update is intended to improve the robustness of the RPKI
      framework by altering the procedure of the original validation
      path that included an "encompassing" condition applied pairwise
      to the certificates used in the validation path.</t>

      <t>The intent of this update is to ensure that all certificates
      on a validation path encompass the resources that are included
      in the validation query, but to remove the "encompassing"
      constraint on the resources used in pairwise comparison. This
      change to the validation procedure reduces the criticality of
      strict orchestration of the sequence of certificate issuance and
      revocation when resources are added or removed from resource
      sets, and can thereby improve the robustness of the RPKI as a
      consequence, without altering the underlying semnatics of the
      association of a public key value across a collection of number
      resources.</t>

    </section>
    <section title="IANA Considerations">
    
      <t>No updates to the registries are suggested by this document.</t>
      
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements">

      <t>Thanks</t>

    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      &RFC5280;
      &RFC6487;
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
